Inventory of the Klaus Kirchner collection
Hoover Institution Archives
- Soviet Central Series, 1941-1945; 1-5 (Box 1-5:)
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 92, 1942 March (Folder 2: 994)
    15x22 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [What is happening in Germany? No. 92... Labour unrest in Düsseldorf... German people are cursing Hitler and his war...]. Drawing by Erich Weinert: [Think about your child!]
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 119, 1942 March (Folder 2: 995)
    14x25 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 119... The Russians are encircling and destroying the German-Fascist invaders...]. Photograph: [These are the new American tanks reaching the Eastern front.]
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 114, 1942 March (Folder 2: 996)
    14x22 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [News from Foreign Countries No. 114... In spring Hitler will have a new front, the Western front…]. Photograph: German POWs write letters to their relatives.
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 93, 1942 March (Folder 2: 997)
    15x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [What is happening in Germany? No. 93... The German economy is not able to supply the material for the spring offensive...]. Photograph: a Soviet commissar is lighting the cigarette for a German POW.
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 121, 1942 March (Folder 2: 998)
    15x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 121... A German pilot is deserting to the Red Army... I must say my welcome was warm and friendly...]. Photograph: a group of POWs.
  - Wie die Kriegsgefangenen in Sowjetrussland leben, Nr. 5, 1942 March (Folder 2: 999)
    14x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [How the POWs are living in Soviet Russia No.5... In Russian captivity I have experienced what real humanity means...]. Photograph: A Soviet commissar is lighting the cigarette for a German POW
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 115, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1000)
    14x21 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [News from Foreign Countries No. 115... Arrival of new American troops in England...]. Photograph: [These are the new American tanks reaching the Eastern front.]
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 94, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1002)
    14x22 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [What is happening in Germany? No. 94... German traffic is without fuel]. Drawing by Erich Weinert: German cripple, his wife and daughter.
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 116, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1004)
    15x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1 - 3.1942 - description: [News from Foreign Countries No. 116... Hitler's hope for the spring offensive has already failed... Soviet Russia knows how to defeat Hitler...]. Photograph: a group of German POWs are surrendering.
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 122, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1005)
    15x23 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 122... Russians clean their soil from the German invaders...]. Photograph: A group of POWs.
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 95, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1006)
    15x23 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [What is happening in Germany? No. 95 ... Increasing dissatisfaction in Berlin... The Nazis are stealing soldier's letters...]. Photograph: Cemetery.
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 117, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1007)
    14x22 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [News from Foreign Countries No. 117... Spring will bring the defeat of Hitler-Germany... Soviet Russia knows how to defeat Hitler... America has built six new battle ships]. Photomontage: abandoned German tanks and vehicles.
  - Oberkommando der Wehrmacht Mitteilungen für die Truppe Nr. 204, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1008)
    19x31 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [High command of the Wehrmacht News for the Troops No. 204 March 1942...]. The Soviet "black" leaflet is on the first glance a pamphlet containing material for the instruction of German soldiers. [... We have to trust the Führer blindly... What will spring have in store for us?... For what are "Iron Crosses" being awarded?...]
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 118, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1010)
    14x21 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [News from Foreign Countries No. 118... Hitler-Germany is condemned to defeat... German-Americans against Hitler...]. Photomontage: [New Russian tanks arrive at the front].
  - Das ist der Schuldige am Tode von 30,000 deutschen Soldaten!, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1011)
    17x25 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [He is responsible for the death of 30,000 German soldiers!...]. Photomontage: [General von Busch - the guilty one...]
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 123, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1012)
    14x22 cm - 2 - preservation: 1 - 3.1942. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 123... The German generals are afraid of the truth...]. Photograph: German POWs are surrendering.
  - Wie die Kriegsgefangenen in Sowjetrussland leben Nr. 7, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1013)
    14x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [How the POWs are living in Soviet Russia No.7... The Russians are treating us very well...]. Photograph: meeting of German POWs.
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 96, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1014)
    14x22 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [What is happening in Germany? No. 96... Not enough weapons in Germany...]
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 119, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1015)
    15x23 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [News from Foreign Countries No. 119... Hitler's spring bluff…]. Photograph: [German POWs are playing chess].
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 124, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1016)
    15x23 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 124... The Russians are cleaning their Land from the German invaders...]. Photograph: German POWs are writing letters.
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 97, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1017)
    14x24 cm - 2 - paper: red - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [What is happening in Germany? No. 97... The German people are cursing Hitler and his war... illegal anti-fascist agitation in Germany...]. Photograph: [POW-orchestra].
  - Deutsche Soldaten! J. STALIN, Der Volkskommissar für Verteidigung..., 1942 March (Folder 2: 1020)
    13x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [German soldiers! J. Stalin, the Peoples Commissar for Defence said in his speech to the Red Army on 23rd February...]. Photograph and caption: German POWs report about the lies they had been told about Soviet commissars and now realize the difference. NOTE: Leaflets 1020-1028 have the same safe conduct and headline: "Deutsche Soldaten! J. STALIN, der Volkskommissar..." followed by different quotes from Stalin's speech on February 23, 1942. The different photographs and captions are described.
  - Deutsche Soldaten! J. STALIN, Der Volkskommissar für Verteidigung..., 1942 March (Folder 2: 1021)
    13x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of photograph and caption: German POWs are fed a well tasting, fat, and nourishing meal.
  - Deutsche Soldaten! J. STALIN, Der Volkskommissar für Verteidigung..., 1942 March (Folder 2: 1022)
  - Deutsche Soldaten! J. STALIN, Der Volkskommissar für Verteidigung..., 1942 March (Folder 2: 1023)
    13x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of photograph and caption: German POW is writing a letter to his relatives after having a good meal.
  - Deutsche Soldaten! J. STALIN, Der Volkskommissar für Verteidigung..., 1942 March (Folder 2: 1024)
    13x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of photograph and caption: Willi Bredel, the well known communist writer, is talking to German POWs from Hamburg.
  - Deutsche Soldaten! J. STALIN, Der Volkskommissar für Verteidigung..., 1942 March (Folder 2: 1025)
    13x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of photograph and caption: German POWs are going to have a rest after having been washed and deloused.
  - Deutsche Soldaten! J. STALIN, Der Volkskommissar für Verteidigung..., 1942 March (Folder 2: 1026)
    13x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of photograph and caption: German POWs are going for a walk after their meal.
  - Deutsche Soldaten! J. STALIN, Der Volkskommissar für Verteidigung..., 1942 March (Folder 2: 1027)
    13x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of photograph and caption: A Russian doctor is treating a German POW.
  - Deutsche Soldaten! J. STALIN, Der Volkskommissar für Verteidigung..., 1942 March (Folder 2: 1028)
    13x21 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of photograph and caption: German POWs are reporting their first impressions in Russian captivity.
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 125, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1029)
    15x23 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 125... Big Russian successes... Hitler is chasing the workers of his war industry to the front...]. Photograph: German POWs at a meeting: [Here they can at last voice their opinion freely for the first time].
  - Wie die Kriegsgefangenen in Sowjetrussland leben Nr. 8, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1030)
    13x23 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [How the POWs are living in Soviet Russia No.8... The Russians gave me back my life... Stalin's words are true.] Photograph: German POWs are listening to phonograph records.]
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 98, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1031)
    15x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [What is happening in Germany? No. 98... Hitler had prepared the war against Russia a long time ago...]. Photograph: a group of German POWs.
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 120, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1032)
    15x22 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [News from Foreign Countries No. 120... Attacks by the English Air Force... appeal by German-Americans to the German people...]. Photograph: German POWs are queuing up for reading material.
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 126, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1035)
    14x22 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 126... Mighty blows of the Red Army against German troops...]. Photograph: German POWs at work.
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 121, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1036)
    14x22 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [News from Foreign Countries No. 121... 44th bombardment of the Krupp factories... Does it pay to continue?...]. Photograph: German POWs are playing mandolins.
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 99, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1037)
    15x23 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [What is happening in Germany? No. 99... The German people are raising to fight against Hitler... Protest of the bishop of Berlin against the misdeeds of the Gestapo...]. Drawing of Erich Weinert: a German cripple, his wife and daughter.
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 127, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1039)
    15x22 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 127...The Red Army is pushing the Germans to the West... German soldiers and officers are surrendering in groups]. Photograph: German troops abandoned canon on their hastily retreat.
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 122, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1040)
    14x23 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [News from Foreign Countries No. 122]. Roosevelt speaking on the weapons and loan program. Photograph: US tanks are reaching the Eastern front.
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 100, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1041)
    14x23 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [What is happening in Germany? No. 100... Unbearable workload in German factories...]. Drawing by Erich Weinert: a German soldier is accusing Hitler.
  - Wie die Kriegsgefangenen in Sowjetrussland leben Nr. 9, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1042)
    13x23 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [How the POWs are living in Soviet Russia No.9... A day in a prisoners of war camp...] - Photograph: German POWs are writing collective letters.].
  - An alle Kameraden der deutschen Wehrmacht Am 4. März 1942 gaben sich..., 1942 March (Folder 2: 1043)
    17x17 cm - 4 - paper: blue - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [To all comrades of the German Wehrmacht. On March 4, 1942, German soldiers surrendered... They had Stalin's order with them...] Two photographs.
  - An alle deutschen Offiziere und..., 1942 March (Folder 2: 1044)
    15x22 cm - 4 - preservation: 1. Description: [To all German officers and soldiers...]. Appeal of German POWs. Photograph: German POWs are signing the appeal.
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 128, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1045)
    15x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 128... German troops which do not surrender will be annihilated...]. Photograph: meeting of German POWs.
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 129, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1046)
    15x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 129... The Russian offensive is continuing... The words of Stalin are the absolute truth...]. Photograph: Germans are surrendering.
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 123, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1047)
    15x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 123…The Russians made Hitler's plan for a spring offensive obsolete…Spring will bring Hitler a new front, the Western front...]. Photograph: German POWs are discussing an appeal addressed to their comrades at the front.
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 124, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1048)
    15x24 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 124... The war aim of the Russian people is guaranteed by Stalin... England's armament is increasing dramatically...] Photograph: German POWs are writing notes for their wall newspaper.
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 101, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1049)
    14x23 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [... German workers are rising to fight against the war... Hitler-fascism is undermining the German youth...]. Photograph: a group of German POWs are being received by the Russians with
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? No. 101, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1050)
    14x22 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [What is happening in Germany? No. 101... Protest of the Bishop of Münster against persecution of Catholics...]. Photograph: a Russian doctor is treating the wound of a German POW.
  - Zur neuen Lüge des Berliner Rundfunks..., 1942 March (Folder 2: 1051)
    18x25 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [About the new lies of Radio Berlin...]. A German victory is being reported but the Soviet Service of Information is emphatically denying this. Poem, author unknown. Caricature: [Goebbels sits in the shelter over there...]
  - Wie die Kriegsgefangenen in Sowjetrussland leben Nr. l0, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1052)
    15x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [How the POWs are living in Soviet Russia No. 10... Seven months in Russian captivity... A German soldier is welcoming Stalin's order...]. Photograph: German POWs will have a rest after having been bathed and deloused...]
  - Soldatenwahrheit gegen Nazilüge..., 1942 March (Folder 2: 1053)
    14x23 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [The truth is being told by a soldier against Nazi-lies... German POWs are describing in a letter the good life in their camp.]
  - Meine Antwort auf die Lügenmärchen..., 1942 March (Folder 2: 1054)
    14x22 cm - 4 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [My answer to propaganda fairytales about Russian captivity...] Facsimiles of POW statements.
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 125, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1055)
    15x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 125... Hitler is leading the German Army to a catastrophe... Rumania refuses to supply cannon fodder... Anti-German demonstrations in Brazil...Unrest of German troops in France...]. Photograph: The German writer Willi Bredel is talking to German POWs.
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 103, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1056)
    14x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [What is happening in Germany? No. 103... Work slower!... The Hitler-organization breeding vice... German officials are demanding of German girls to have babies from soldiers going back to the front... Many girls kill their babies born out of wedlock...]. Photograph: a group of German POW is talking laughingly with a Soviet commissar.
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 130, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1057)
    15x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 130... The successful offensive of the Russians continues... The Russian Cossacks are frightening the German invaders]. Photograph: German soldiers in a meeting. [Here they can finally voice their opinion freely.]
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 126, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1061)
    15x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 126... The Russian Army is beating the German invaders... Soldiers from Berlin refuse to fight...]. Photograph: German POW writing home to his relatives.
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 104, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1062)
    15x22 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [What is happening in Germany? No. 104... Berliners are calling for the deposal of Hitler...]. Göring caricature.
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 132, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1063)
    15x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 132...The Russian Army is beating the German invaders... Soldiers from Berlin refuse to fight...]. Photograph: Russian soldier - German soldier [One is a blind tool in the hands of Hitler, the other knows what he is fighting for.]
  - Gruss aus dem Gefangenenlager Nr. 2, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1067)
    15x23 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [Greetings from the POW-camp No.2...] A poem and two drawings by Erich Weinert. [Our camp. Here we are sitting warm, here we are satisfied]
  - Gruss aus dem Gefangenenlager Nr. 3, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1068)
    15x23 cm - 2 - paper: green - preservation: 1. Description: Greetings from the POW-camp No. 3... A poem and two drawings by Erich Weinert. [The dream is over...]
  - AUFRUF der Konferenz kriegsgefangener Unteroffiziere der deutschen..., 1942 March (Folder 2: 1072)
    20x28 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [Appeal of the conference of non-commissioned officers of the Wehrmacht... To the German Army and the German people...]. Facsimile of appeal.
  - Sie alle haben einen Wunsch…, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1073)
    14x23 cm - 2 - paper: green or rose - preservation: 1. Description: [They all have one wish - nothing but going home...]. Drawing by Erich Weinert. [Daddy, do come home!]
  - Wie die Kriegsgefangenen in Sowjetrussland leben Nr. 11, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1075)
    13x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [How the POWs are living in Soviet Russia No. 11... First impressions in Russian captivity... The commissars are lovely and educated men...] Photograph: German POWs.
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 105, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1076)
    15x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [What is happening in Germany? No. 105... Austrian people against Hitler... Women are demonstrating in Dresden. The radio station "Free Germany" is reporting... Many children die because there is no medical help... The demonstration was dispersed by SS formations firing into the crowd...]. Caricature: [Göring is looking for fresh cannon fodder.]
  - Der Rassenhass dient den Herrschenden. Den Schaffenden bringt er Verderben und..., 1942 March (Folder 2: 1077)
    14x25 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [Racial hatred is serving the ruling classes, it is bringing the working classes ruin and disgrace... In Germany one million have been sterilized... The "Stürmer" is poisoning the fantasy of the German youth with pornography]. Drawing: [This is Hitler's race-theory in reality.]
  - Vorbei ist die Zeit der Erfolge Hitlers. Deutsche Soldaten! Die deutsche..., 1942 March (Folder 2: 1078)
    14x23 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description: [Gone are the times of Hitler's success... The defeat of Hitler-Germany is unavoidable!...]. Drawing probably by Erich Weinert: [German soldier in a snow storm].
  - Auslands-Nachrichten Nr. 127, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1079)
    15x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from Foreign Countries No. 127... The Red Army destroyed the legend of invincibility of Hitler's Army...]. Photograph: German soldiers are surrendering.
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 106, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1080)
    16x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [What is happening in Germany? No. 106... Who is enriching himself during the war?... Catholics against Hitler... Catholic Bishops Faulhaber, Wurm, Preilling, von Galen...]. Photograph: German POWs reading a wall newspaper.
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 134, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1081)
    15x22 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [... Health and morale of German soldiers have been badly shaken...]. Photograph: Russian commissar and a group of German POWs.
  - Auslands-Nachrichten, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1083)
    14x22 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description: [News from Foreign Countries No. 128... The Soviet Japanese agreement... 500 English bombers attack Essen...]. Photograph: A Russian doctor is helping a wounded German soldier.
  - Wie die Kriegsgefangenen in Sowjetrussland leben Nr. 12, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1084)
    15x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [How the POWs are living in Soviet Russia No. 12... How we can put an end to this war...] - Photograph: German POWs are being received with a well made, fat, nourishing meal.
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 135, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1085)
    14x22 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 135... Russians encircle and destroy German fortifications...]. Photomontage: Dead German soldiers.
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. 107, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1086)
    13x23 cm - 2 - paper: rose - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [What is happening in Germany? No. 107... Hitler is no longer talking about his spring-offensive...]. Photograph: German POWs going for a walk after their meal.
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 136, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1088)
    15x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 136... Mighty Russian blows against German troops...]. Photograph: German cemetery.
  - Frontnachrichten Nr. 137, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1089)
    15x23 cm - 2 - preservation: 1. Description of leaflet newspaper: [News from the Front No. 137... Rich booty of Russian troops.. .]. Photograph: A Soviet commissar is talking to German POWs...]
  - Was geht in Deutschland vor? Nr. l08, 1942 March (Folder 2: 1090)